Finding Aid for George Katona Papers 1929-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Katona Papers 1929-1981
Katona, George, 1901-
2 linear feet
Professor of economics and psychology, and research coordinator for the Survey Research Center, Institute for Social Research, at the University of Michigan. Research reports, addresses and speeches, miscellaneous correspondence, personal material, and photographs.
85237 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Katona family members (donor no. 6658 ) and came to the library in 1981-1982.
The collection is open for research.
George Katona was born in Budapest, Hungary on November 6,1901. He received his Ph.D. in Psychology from the University of Goettingen, Germany in 1921. For several years, first in Germany, then in the United States, Katona worked alternately as a psychologist, an economist, and as a journalist. After 1938 he began to integrate his diverse professional interests at the New School for Social Research, New York, the University of Chicago, and as an employee of the federal government in Washington. From 1946 until his retirement in 1972, Dr. Katona has been affiliated with the University of Michigan as Professor of Economics, Professor of Psychology, and Research Coordinator for the Survey Research Center, Institute for Social Research. He founded and for many years directed the Surveys of Consumer Finances, and devised the Index of Consumer Sentiment.
Katona was a Fellow of the American Psychological Association, American Statistical Association and the American Economic Association. He has authored numerous articles and books, several of which have been translated into foreign languages. Katona summarized his theoretical approach and his findings in Psychological Economics (Elsevier, 1972). In 1977 the University of Amsterdam, Holland, awarded him an honorary degree of Doctor of Economic Sciences. In the same year the American Psychological Association bestowed on him its Distinguished Professional Contribution Award.
Throughout his career, Katona sought to study economic problems in terms of psychology. A pioneer in the field of consumer psychology and economic forecasting. Katona was described by some as the "dean of behavioral economics". He died in 1981 at the age of 79.
The George Katona Collection consists primarily of reports and speeches (in typewritten manuscript form) produced during his association with the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan, and with the United States Government. Also included are reviews of his published works, and reprints of those articles of his not listed in his bibliography. In addition, there is a small amount of correspondence concerning the relationship between the Institute for Social Research and various departments at the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Katona, George, 1901-1981; Social surveys--Research.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Charitable organizations.; Katona, George, 1901-1981
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal Papers
  - Biographical and bibliographical materials (Box 1)
    (1)
  - Correspondence 1929-1938 (Box 1)
    (2)
  - Correspondence 1961-1972 (Box 1)
    (3)
  - Correspondence 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    (4)
  - University of Michigan Memos 1965-1971 (Box 1)
    (5)
  - University of Michigan Memos 1972-1980 (Box 1)
    (6)
  - Institute for Social Research, Press Releases 1963-1981 (Box 1)
    (7)
  - Reviews of published works (Box 1)
    (8)
  - Obituaries (Box 1)
    (9)
  - Memorial Service July 1, 1981 (Box 1)
    (10)
- Research Reports
  - Psychological Implications of the Inflation Problem 1942 (Box 1)
    (11)
  - Report for the Division of Program Surveys, United States Department of Agriculture 1945 (Box 1)
    (12)
  - Reports for the Survey Research Center, University of Michigan
    - Four Families Discuss Their Financial Position 1948 (Box 1)
      (13)
    - Validity of Consumer Expectations 1949 (Box 1)
      (14)
    - Postwar Income Changes of Identical Consumer Units 1949 (Box 1)
      (15)
    - Die Erforschung Der Offentlichen Meinung 1950 (Box 1)
      (16)
    - Reports on Activities in Germany 1950, 1953 (Box 1)
      (17)
    - Comments on the Reports: "Consumer Survey Statistics" (Smithies Committee) and "Statistics on Saving" (Goldsmith Committee) 1955 (Box 1)
      (18)
    - Consumer Psychology: The Growth of a Movement 1961 (Box 1)
      (19)
    - Consumer Behavior in Our Changing Environment 1961 (Box 1)
      (20)
    - Advertising in a Mass Consumption Society 1964 (Box 1)
      (21)
    - Adaptive Theory of Consumer Behavior 1967 (Box 1)
      (22)
    - Consumer Savings: Preference for and Use of Savings Accounts 1968 (Box 1)
      (23)
    - The Impact of the Tax Surcharge of 1968 on Consumer Expenditures (Box 1)
      (24)
    - Installment Debt 1970 (Box 1)
      (25)
    - Aspirations and Economic Trends 1970 (Box 1)
      (26)
    - Social Statistics on Consumption and the Consumer 1970 (Box 1)
      (27)
    - Consumer Aspirations Influence the Economy 1970 (Box 1)
      (28)
    - Proposed Panel Analysis for Spring Publication 1970 (Box 1)
      (29)
    - Economic Behavior Program, 25th Anniversary Report 1970 (Box 1)
      (30)
    - Attitudes Toward Mutual Fund Shares 1970 (Box 1)
      (31)
    - Ownership and Purchases of Stocks and Mutual Fund Shares 1971 (Box 1)
      (32)
    - On Studies of Personal Savings 1971 (Box 1)
      (33)
    - Prospects for Personal Savings 1971 (Box 1)
      (34)
    - Violence Project 1971 (Box 1)
      (35)
    - Methodological Studies on Consumer Anticipation 1971 (Box 1)
      (36)
    - Product Quality: Economic and Psychological Considerations 1971 (Box 1)
      (37)
    - Theory of Expectations 1971 (Box 1)
      (38)
    - The Function of Advertising of Standardized Products 1972 (Box 1)
      (39)
    - Cognitive Processes in Social Learning 1972 (Box 1)
      (40)
    - Change in Long Range Attitudes 1972 (Box 1)
      (41)
    - Memorandum on the Consumer's Way of Understanding Food Ads and Price Advertising, 19719 (Box 1)
      (42)
    - Volatility of Consumer Attitudes 1976 (Box 1)
      (43)
    - Consumer Sentiment and Economic Trends 1977 (Box 1)
      (44)
    - Measures of Uncertainty 1977 (Box 1)
      (45)
    - Toward a Macro Psychology 1978 (Box 1)
      (46)
    - Fourier Charts 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      (47)
    - Survey Indications of Unfavorable Economic Trends 1978 (Box 1)
      (48)
    - Behavioral Science and Public Policy 1979 (Box 1)
      (49)
    - Middle Range Economic Trends 1980 (Box 1)
      (50)
    - Expectations in Economics 1981 (Box 1)
      (51)
    - Interdisciplinary Research 1981 (Box 1)
      (52)
    - Economic Psychology; Evaluation and Prospects 1981 (Box 1)
      (53)
    - Consumer Behavior in the Purchase of Durable Goods undated (Box 1)
      (54)
- Addresses and Speeches
  - Consumer Investment and Business Investments 1960 (Box 1)
    (55)
  - Vienna Conference 1962 (Box 1)
    (56)
  - Statement for the Joint Economic Committee 1962 (Box 1)
    (57)
  - Strengthening the Behavioral Sciences 1962 (Box 1)
    (58)
  - Consumer Attitudes and Expectations 1968 (Box 1)
    (59)
  - Paper at Yale 1970 (Box 1)
    (60)
  - Measurement and Predictive Value of Attitudes and Expectations 1970 (Box 1)
    (61)
  - Economic Outlook Conference 1971 (Box 1)
    (62)
  - Boston Presentation 1972 (Box 1)
    (63)
  - Savings Bond Committee Conference 1973 (Box 1)
    (64)
  - Economic Indicators and Consumer Motivation 1974 (Box 1)
    (65)
  - Attitudes Towards Trust Companies 1976 (Box 1)
    (66)
  - Amsterdam Speech 1977 (Box 1)
    (67)
  - Dinner Speech 1977 (Box 1)
    (68)
  - American Economic Association Meeting 1977 (Box 1)
    (69)
  - CUNA-San Francisco Speech 1977 (Box 1)
    (70)
  - Finlay Carpenter Lecture 1978 University of Michigan (Box 1)
    (71)
  - Brooklyn College Speech "The Psychology of Inflation," 1980 (Box 1)
    (72)
  - CBS-TV, WBBM-TV research materials (Box 1)
    (73)
  - University of Illinois Honorary Doctoral Speech 1981 (Box 1)
    (74)
  - Association of Business Economists undated (Box 1)
    (75)
  - Consumer Durable Spending undated (Box 1)
    (76)
- Publications, clippings, etc
  - Foreign Periodicals containing Dr. Katona's articles (Box 2)
    (77)
  - Unpublished Manuscript Currency Warfare and Stabilization, undated (Box 2)
    (78)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper clippings (Box 2)
    (79)
  - Reprints of Periodical Articles not listed in his bibliographies (Box 2)
    (80)
  - George Katona & A Emergencia Da Economia Psicologica Nos Estrados Unidos, Thesis by Luiza Branco Fernandes, Universidade De Sao Paulo, 1979 (Box 2)
  - The Investment Needs of Individuals, Corporate Planning Report, Merrill, Lynch, Pierce, Fenner, and Smith, Inc., 1970 (Box 2)
  - The Founder's Symposium: The Institute for Social Research Honoring George Katona 1979 (Box 2)
  - Parlin National Marketing Award (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    Photographs include portraits of George Katona and picture of his wife in March of Dimes publicity scene.